This is J. Krishnamurti's discussion with students in San Diego, California, 1970.
Krishnamurti What shall we talk over together this morning?
This is supposed to be a discussion and I think the word discussion is not right.
It is more a dialogue, exchange, not of opinions, because that will lead us nowhere.
Or indulging in mere intellectual cleverness will have very little meaning.
Because truth is not to be found through exchange of opinions or of ideas.
So, if we are to talk over together any problem,
it must be on the level which is not intellectual or emotional or sentimental,
but problems that really affect one in one's daily living.
And from there go into it. Yes, sir.
Questioner I live in conflict with myself.
I am a vegetarian from Rofnuda. I don't kill.
But to solve the problem that communism takes not over,
I think this war against communism is in a certain sense of self-mortgaging justified.
I would like to find out with you if I am right or wrong.
The gentleman says that he is a vegetarian, doesn't kill,
and the fight against communism is self-protective response. Is that it, sir?
Q. Yes.
K. That's really very funny.
Q. You must understand, I lived ten years under communism.
I was in a Russian concentration camp when I was in a communist prison.
They understand only one language and it is power.
K. So what is the question, sir?
Q. The question is, is this war self-protection or not?
K. I believe every war, every group that lead to war,
the politicians that bring about wars,
they always say, don't they, that it is self-protective war.
Is that what you want to really discuss?
Wars have always been, whether they are offensive or defensive, but they are wars.
Killing each other has been a kind of peculiar, monstrous game
throughout the centuries.
And we are still, unfortunately, those so-called educated, cultured,
still indulging in the most savage form of butchery.
Could we go into the question of,
if that is what interests some of you,
what is deep violence, this aggression in man,
and whether it is at all possible to be free of it?
Could we discuss that?
Do you really want to go into it?
No?
You know, there have been groups
who have said that they will, under no circumstances, express violence,
live a peaceful life, surrounded by people who are very aggressive, violent,
a kind of nucleus amongst people who are savage, brutal, violent.
And if one has observed,
and if you'll forgive me talking about it a little bit about myself,
I don't read books.
I don't read, the speaker doesn't read the Gita,
the Upanishads, the Bible, you know, all the philosophy and all that.
But I think what is important is,
if we could go into this deeply,
into this question of aggression and violence,
then perhaps it would be worthwhile
and see how far the mind can be absolutely rid of this.
Could we go into it?
Because you see, I feel very strongly
that there is no love in any form,
if there is any spark or touch of violence in the mind.
And how does the mind free itself of its accumulated violence,
cultured violence, self-protective violence,
the violence of aggression,
the violence of competition,
the violence of trying to be somebody,
the violence of trying to discipline oneself according to a pattern.
Please follow all this.
Trying to become somebody,
trying to suppress, trying to bully oneself,
brutalise oneself in order to be,
all such forms of violence,
killing animals, killing the neighbour, killing the – you know.
So,
there are so many different kinds of violence.
Shall we go into each violence,
or shall we take the whole structure of violence?
Not bit by bit.
Can you look at the whole spectrum of violence?
Not one part of it.
Q. May I ask you the source?
May I ask you what you feel is the source of violence?
K. What is the source of violence?
The source of violence is the me,
the ego, the self,
which expresses itself in so many ways,
in division,
in trust,
in trying to become or be somebody,
in dividing the me and the not-me,
the me that divides itself as the unconscious and the conscious,
the me that identifies with the family and not the family,
the community and not the community, and so on and on.
It's like a drop of a stone in a lake,
the waves spread, spread, spread,
but the centre is the me.
And as long as that in any form survives,
very subtly or grossly, there must be violence.
You see, you asked a question,
what is the root cause of violence,
but that is a question
which by trying to find out what the cause is,
we think we shall be rid of it.
So shall we tackle that first thing?
By thinking or enquiring into the cause of violence,
we think we shall be able to get rid of it.
Don't we?
I say to myself, if I know why I am brutal,
I have finished with brutality.
And I spend weeks and months and years searching for the cause,
or reading the explanations given by experts, specialists
or specialists of the various causes of violence or aggression.
But at the end of the volume,
whether it's a small volume or ten volumes,
I am still violent.
Right?
So, do we enquire into this question of violence
through the discovery of the cause and the effect,
or take the cause, the effect,
and take the whole of it and look at it?
Because the cause becomes the effect,
and the effect becomes the cause.
It's a chain process, isn't it?
I don't know if you...
There is no cause and effect so markedly different.
It is a chain,
a cause becoming the effect,
and the effect becoming the cause.
And we can go along this process indefinitely,
but whereas if we could, I suggest,
if we could look at this whole problem of violence in man
and see how to resolve it, how to end it,
how to put a... comprehend it so vitally that you come to an end.
Could we do that?
The me and the not me,
is it the effect of the culture,
the society in which we live,
or is it innate,
or is it born with us?
Again, can you divide the culture from yourself and yourself
from the society?
Are they both the same, interrelated?
The me, my greed, my problems, my desires, my anxieties,
my fears, my hopes, my anguishing fulfilments and desires,
my hopes, my anguishing fulfilments and despairs, deep sorrows,
are also the product of my neighbour,
of the community I live in.
They are both interrelated, I cannot separate it
and say, this is me and that is society.
Once the separation has taken place,
as in the case of most people,
then this me becomes more self-centred, more active,
more divisive and so on.
So again we come to the question,
can we take violence as a whole,
including the me, which is the origin of violence,
and the society in which we live is the origin of violence.
Can we do that? Not separate it.
We have built a society which is violent,
and we, as human beings, are violent,
and so the environment in which we live,
the culture in which we live is the product of our endeavour,
is the product of our struggle, of our pain,
of our appalling brutalities.
For me, the most important thing is,
is it possible to end?
Can one end this tremendous violence in one?
That is really the question.
Shall we do that? Can we discuss that?
So don't let's go back to the cause again at the end of it.
Q. Is it possible to transform by not eliminating or ending
the sense of each other's intentions?
K. Is it possible to transform it, not end it?
We are going to find out.
Because, look, violence is a form of energy.
And that energy, utilised in a certain way, becomes aggression.
So we are not trying to transform or change, but understand it,
comprehend it so fully that one is free of it,
the mind has gone beyond it,
whether it has transcended it or transformed it and ended it,
that is irrelevant.
Those are verbal means of communication.
So can we discuss this?
Is it possible – not possible, it is possible –
these words –
to enquire together into this question of violence and going beyond it?
Shall we do this, sir? Yes, sir?
Q. If our action, which we say is the effect, is the act of violence,
then the cause is violence in us, which the action is an expression of.
Now, we are violent and the me is violent,
so what is that doing for the me, for me to be violent?
What is that thing that is being expressed when I am violent?
K. I see what you mean, sir. Is this what you mean?
And please correct it.
The me is, we said, the centre of violence.
How does that me come into being,
which then protects itself in order to survive,
and in the protection of itself, in the security of itself,
it must bring about violence?
So you are asking, how does this me come about?
Which is the very centre of aggression.
And aggression is the effect of the me
who is separating itself from the you
and therefore resisting you,
and therefore becoming aggressive.
So you are asking, are you not, sir,
how does the me come into being,
and if that is the cause of all violence in humanity,
then the very transformation of the me
will end all violence.
That is what we are trying to find out,
to enquire into the ending
or drying up the source of aggression.
Now let's proceed, sir, let's get going,
otherwise we can go on verbalisation forever.
Now, how do we grapple with this question?
Abstractly or directly realising that human beings are violent.
How do you think about violence?
How do you look at violence?
Do you look at violence in another or violence in yourself?
Please do watch it, please listen to the question.
How do you know you are violent?
Conflict is violence.
And when there is conflict, is one aware that one is violent?
How do you know violence?
This is really a complex question, knowing.
Look, sir, when I say, I know you,
what does that mean, I know?
I know you as you were yesterday when I met you,
or ten years ago when I met you.
But between ten years ago and now,
you might have changed and I might have changed,
therefore I don't know you.
I know you only ten years ago or ten days ago,
therefore I can never say I know you.
Do please understand this simple thing first.
Therefore I can never say,
I can always say I have been violent,
but I don't know what violence now is.
You understand what I am talking?
Are we...
So how do you know violence
when you say, I am violent, I am angry,
I hate somebody – I hope you don't –
but when you say these things, what do you mean by it?
Right?
Look, sir, I am angry.
You say something to me which irritates my nerves
and all the rest of the organical process,
I am angry.
And then I say afterwards, second later,
I say, by Jove, I have been angry.
At the moment of anger I don't recognise it,
only later I recognise it.
Now, the recognition,
you have to examine the structure of recognition,
because if you don't understand the structure of recognition
you won't be able to meet anger afresh.
I don't know if you...
Look, I am angry,
and I realise I am angry a moment later.
The realisation is the recognition, I have been angry.
The recognition takes place when I have been angry before,
otherwise I don't know it is anger.
So when I recognise it,
I recognise it only because I have known it before.
See what has happened.
The past interferes with the present,
and then I say I am angry.
So I am always translating the present reaction
in terms of the past.
So can I, without translating the present response with the past,
can I look at the response anew,
you understand, with a fresh mind?
Are we meeting each other?
No, please do it.
Look, you call me a fool,
and my whole blood, every thing,
comes to the surface and says, you are another.
And what has taken place in me, emotionally, inwardly?
I have an image about myself.
And that image says, I am not a fool,
I have made that image into something
which I think is desirable, noble, worthwhile,
and you are insulting that image.
And that image responds, which is the old.
You are following?
And so the old responds.
So the next question is, can the response,
can the response not be related to the old,
therefore an interval between the old and the new response?
You follow?
Can the old be dormant, be hesitant,
so as to allow the new to take place?
You understand?
I think that is where the whole problem is.
Q. Are you saying then that violence, the root of violence,
all violence is just confusion of what isn't and what is?
K. No, sir, no, sir, no, sir.
Look, let's begin again.
We are violent.
Throughout man's existence,
human beings have been violent and are violent.
I want to find out as a human being
how to transcend this violence, how to go beyond it.
What am I to do?
Because I see what violence has done in the world,
how it has destroyed every form of friendship,
every form of relationship,
how it has brought deep agony in oneself, misery.
I see all that.
And I say to myself,
I want to live really a peaceful life
in which there is deep abundance of love,
and the violence must disappear, or must go, etc.
Now, what am I to do?
First, I mustn't escape from it.
Right?
Let's be sure of that.
I must not escape from the fact I am violent.
Escaping being, condemning it.
Right?
Justifying it,
or even naming that I am violent.
You are following?
Because the naming is a form of condemnation,
is a form of justification.
So, first I have to realise
the mind must not be distracted from this fact of violence,
either in seeking the cause
or in the explanation of the cause,
or naming the fact that I am violent,
or justifying it, condemning it, trying to get rid of it.
Those are all forms of distraction
from the fact of violence. Right?
This is clear, is it?
So, the mind must be absolutely clear
that there is no escape from it.
Not the exercise of will, who says, I will conquer it,
because will is the very essence of violence.
I don't know if you are...
Q. Are we trying to find some order in it, order in the violence?
K. What, sir?
Q. Order in why we are violent?
K. Are we trying to bring order into violence? Is that it?
Q. Well, basically, are we trying to find what violence is
by finding order in it, or the order in ourselves?
K. No, sir, no, sir. How can there be order in violence?
Violence is disorder.
Do please go with me a little bit.
First, no escape from it, of any kind,
intellectual, explanatory, justification.
See the difficulty of this,
because our mind is so cunning, so sharp to escape,
because it doesn't know what to do with it.
It is not capable of dealing with it,
or it thinks it is not capable, therefore it escapes.
Look, sir, most of us know what loneliness is, don't we?
Don't you? Being lonely.
And being lonely, not knowing what to do with it,
being afraid of it, we move away from it.
Right? We escape from it.
Or try to fill that emptiness by knowledge,
by all kinds of things.
All those are distractions from the fact of loneliness.
Right? And therefore it is still there.
So what one has to realise first is not to escape.
Realise that every form of escape, distraction,
a movement away, only sustains violence.
So the mind then is confronted with the fact,
with what is, and nothing else.
Right?
Are we doing this, please?
This is a discussion, not a talk by me.
Q. The thought of loneliness, it's felt that if you say it and I hear it,
and I say to myself, I am lonely,
I immediately feel that I have escaped in saying that.
K. Of course, of course you have escaped when you say, I am lonely.
You know the fact of loneliness, you know what it means.
Don't you?
Look, sir, it's so simple.
Look, sir, when you look at a tree – do watch it –
when you look at a tree, if you say, what a beautiful tree that is,
your mind has already gone away from observing the tree, isn't it?
No?
So to look at the tree is not to say it's a beautiful tree.
Therefore your attention is completely looking.
Right?
So when you say, what a beautiful river that is,
what a lovely view that is, you have already gone.
Yes, sir, yes. Behind you, sir, behind.
Q. So whether it's violence or loneliness, you don't name it.
K. We are going to find out, sir.
Do it, sir, do it, and you will have answered it yourself.
When you name it, you are relating it, the name, to the past.
Therefore you are looking at it
with the eyes that have been touched by the past.
Therefore you are not looking at it afresh. That's all.
You get the point?
You look at violence – please do listen to this –
you look at violence with eyes that have condemned,
that are conditioned, that are justifying,
that say violence is necessary to live in this monstrous society,
violence is part of nature, part – look, nature kills, and so on.
You follow?
With the eyes that are conditioned to look,
with condemnation or justification or resistance,
what we are saying is to look at it afresh,
anew, and you can only do that when you become aware
that you are identifying what you see with what you already know,
and therefore not looking at it afresh. Right?
Just get this point, please.
Just a minute, sir, your turn will come. Just a minute, sir.
Look, sir, I look at my wife or my husband – I'm not married –
I look at my wife or my husband.
Do I ever really look at her or him,
or do I look at her with the image that I have so carefully built
for 30, 40, 50 years, or 10 days,
and she does the same with me?
And therefore our relationship is between the images
and not actual relationship.
You are following this?
Do you? If you do, then break the image.
So the question then arises,
how is the image formed,
what is the mechanism that forms images?
Q. There is a space between your perception and your response.
That would be time, I suppose.
K. Yes, sir, that's right, but go into it a little more, you will see it.
My wife says to me, you are an ass.
I don't like it.
And that has left a mark on my mind.
Do this, sir, you have left a mark on my mind.
And she says something else, that also leaves a mark on my mind.
So these marks are the images.
Now when she says to me, I am a fool,
if I am aware at that minute – you understand? – aware,
give attention, then there is no marking at all.
You follow it? Because she may be right.
Therefore I am attentive, watching.
So inattention breeds images.
Attention frees the mind from the image. Got this?
You understand, sir? This is very simple.
In the same way, when I am angry,
when I am angry,
to be completely attentive,
not let inattention come in,
which is to allow the past to come and interfere
with the actual perception of anger at the moment.
Got it?
Right?
Q. Is that not an act of will? K. No, we said that.
Is that not an act of will?
We said will is in essence violence.
You know what? Wait a minute, let's examine what will is.
What is will?
I want to do that, I won't have that,
I shall do that.
I have resisted, I demand – will, desire.
Which is what?
Which is a form of resistance, isn't it?
When you say, I will that,
it is a form of resistance.
And resistance is violence.
Yes, sir?
Q. Can you suggest a way of going about
answering the questions which you raise?
I refer to, number one,
your comments that it is better to be aware
than to rationalise.
Perhaps I am paraphrasing you wrong,
but as soon as you use words to rationalise
and try to determine an answer,
you are defeating your own attempts
to arrive at an answer to the questions that you raise.
K. I don't quite follow, sir.
Q. I am asking possibly
if there is some non-verbal internal communication
that you are referring to
in order to answer some of the questions that you ask.
K. I don't quite understand this.
Wait a minute, sir.
Q. I was going to say what he is saying.
Is there – if I may say so.
Q. Go right ahead. I hope so.
I hope you can describe it better than I do.
Q. What you are saying is the what is,
and then there is the response to the what is, which is the memory.
Now he is saying,
is there something else besides the memory of the past
in which there is a non-verbal communication of knowing?
Is there another way of knowing other than being the past?
Is there another communication, another...?
Are you trying to say, ask, sir, is there a communion which is non-verbal?
Q. I guess what I am really trying to say is
that you are trying to talk to something that is in the essence
within a person, within each one of us.
K. No, sir, I don't know...
Q. Maybe I am...
Q. Is there a time to describe that which is indescribable?
Is that not it?
K. No, sir, don't let's go off, please.
I am trying to... Look, we are trying to find out
whether violence can end.
That's all. Don't let's go off to something else.
May I take my coat off?
Q. Can I try that question another way?
I follow you when you say that we avoid the problem often
of seeking an answer.
K. That's right, sir.
Q. That gets us away from the what is.
Q. And in your writings you said the answer is in the problem.
K. That's right, sir.
Now, I want to know how to look at that what is.
Q. Okay. And how do I know the answer when I found the answer?
What is the knowing process?
Or do I only know what the answer was since thought is old?
K. That's part of my question.
What is the question, sir?
Q. If I know the answer, if I focus on an attention,
my attention on a problem,
whether it's violence or loneliness or whatever,
how is it if I really pay attention to the problem,
to say, that's the answer,
or am I thinking then and thought is old?
K. Then there is no problem, sir.
No, no, no, please, please, please, do...
Please don't waste your energy clapping.
It's not worth it.
No, please, sir, do listen to this.
You see, we are looking at life,
living and everything with the eyes
that have been so burdened with the past
that our eyes never see anything new.
Now, we are trying to find out
what the transcending of violence is.
I am saying, don't escape from it first,
verbally or non-verbally,
don't move away from that central fact of violence.
Then the next question is,
how do you know it is violence?
You understand?
You only know it because you are able to recognise it
because you have been violent.
But when you look at it without naming,
without justifying, condemning,
which are all the conditioning of the past,
then you are looking at it with fresh eyes, aren't you?
Then is it violence?
Oh, no, don't say, no, sir,
this is one of the most difficult things to do,
because all our living is the past.
Do you know what it is to live in the present?
Q. Why is it important?
K. Why is it important?
Why do you ask that question, why is it important?
Q. Why are we trying to understand
why do we want to lead a life of love?
K. Why do you want to lead a life of love?
I don't.
I want to lead – not even I don't want to –
I see violence and I see the misery it brings about
to the mother, to the man, to human beings,
and I ask myself, as a human being, can this end?
And in enquiring into the question of ending,
I find out what it is to live peacefully, that's all.
Not that I want to end, which is another form of action of will.
Sir, look, therefore, then the next question is,
the mind is the result of the past.
Right?
The mind recognises violence, names it,
and it moves away from it.
Now, when the mind doesn't name it,
can the mind look at what it has called violence?
Then is there such a thing as violence?
And to look, your mind must be extraordinarily free of the past.
Right?
To look at my wife or my husband,
the mind must be free of the image that it has built,
the image being the past.
To understand that,
and to be aware at the moment of the insult or the flattery,
to be aware at that moment.
If the mind is not aware,
it has already become inattentive and therefore building an image.
This is clear, is it?
Are you doing this?
Q. You say free, be free of it, that includes a lot more.
How far does that go?
Q. Would you mind freedom, would you go into that?
K. Would you go into freedom? What does it mean?
We'll come to that, sir, presently.
So, there are all the deep down
angers, frustrations, resistances.
The mind must also be free of that, mustn't it?
The mind can be free of active violence in the present.
Right?
Are you following this?
I am asking, can the mind be free
of all the unconscious accumulations
of hate, anger, bitterness,
which are there deep down?
You follow? How is this to be done?
Q. Why is this to be done?
K. The gentleman says, why should it be done?
Q. Why not? Well, why not, too?
K. Oh, no, come off it.
Why should it be done and why not?
Then we end up in – you know.
It should be done because, sir,
a man who wants to live at peace
and to bring about a world that is peaceful
must enquire into all this,
must, as a human being, see if he can be free from it.
And that's what we are trying to do.
Q. But if one sees his violence in oneself
and outside of oneself,
how does one keep from being depressed or disturbed by it?
K. Excuse me?
Q. How does one keep from being depressed or disturbed by it?
K. How does one keep from being depressed or disturbed by it?
K. How do – if one is clear and is free of this violence,
you are asking, how can one be free of depression?
Q. No, one sees the violence.
K. About you.
Ah, I see.
If one is free of this violence in oneself,
and when you see violence outside of you,
doesn't it depress you?
What are you to do?
Is that it?
What are you to do is to teach another.
Sir, teaching another is the highest profession in the world,
not for money,
not for your big bank account,
just to teach, to tell another,
tell another, look, you can live differently, for God's sake, look.
Q. What is the easiest way to teach that?
K. What is the easiest way? Go to college.
No, no, no, this is becoming a circus.
Sir, you teach another
by teaching him and therefore learning yourself.
In teaching him, you are learning.
You understand?
First you have learnt, accumulated knowledge,
then you inform,
whereas you are not learning.
You inform, whereas you yourself are violent,
understanding yourself is to help another to understand it.
And therefore the teaching is the learning.
Sir, you don't see all the beauty of all this.
Too bad.
So let's go on.
Sir, I mean, don't you want to know from your heart what love is?
Don't you? No?
He doesn't know.
Isn't it a human cry, which has been for millennia,
to find out how to live peacefully,
how to have real abundance, compassion?
And that can only come into being when there is no violence,
when there is real sense of non-me.
You understand?
And that's what we are enquiring into.
And we say, look, to find that out, don't escape,
whether it is loneliness, whether it is anger,
whether it is bitterness, look at it without any escape.
The escape is the naming of it also.
So when you are bitter, don't name it, look at it.
And then, see, if you don't name, does bitterness exist?
You understand? Yes, sir?
Q. Why is the animal, which apparently has no name but not me,
why is it violent?
K. Why is the animal, which apparently doesn't name,
Is the animal asking the question
or the human being asking the question?
I am not being insulting, sir, but I am asking.
The animal is hungry.
We are supposed to be intelligent and attack the animal
to eat it, for sport and all the rest of the ugly business.
With our violent eyes, we look at the animal.
So, sir, please, let's stick to... Yes, madame?
Q. Excuse me. I'd like to ask two questions.
We've established there's violence in all of our lives,
but what I'm waiting for is how do we get rid of this violence?
I'm showing it to you, madame.
I'm showing it to you.
Q. I'm missing the point that I'm afraid.
You mean merely by facing the fact that there is violence.
No, madame, it's much more complex than that.
Q. And one more question.
Do you advocate getting rid of all violence
or is some violence healthy in everyone's life?
Q. I don't mean physical violence.
I mean getting rid of frustrations.
Can this be helpful?
Or are you trying to keep you from being frustrated?
K. No, madame. Look, answer the second question.
Why are we frustrated?
Have you ever asked yourself why you are frustrated?
To answer that question, have you ever asked what is fulfilment?
Why you want to fulfil?
And is there such a thing as fulfilment?
Please, answer it.
This is a discreet question.
Please, answer it. This is a discussion.
Is there such a thing as fulfilment?
What is it that is fulfilling?
The me?
The me that is violent?
The me that is separating?
The me that says, I'm bigger than you?
The me that pursues ambition, fame, notoriety,
what it will, and because it wants to achieve,
therefore it's frustrated when it cannot achieve,
and therefore becomes bitter,
therefore is there such a thing as fulfilment?
Or only the me wanting to expand itself,
and when it cannot expand it feels frustrated,
and therefore bitter.
And that bitterness, that desire to expand is violence.
Now, when you see that, the truth of that,
then there is no fulfilment at all,
therefore there is no frustration. Oh, Lord!
Yes, sir?
Plants and animals are both living things,
they both try to survive.
Do you draw a distinction between killing animals to eat
and killing plants to eat, if so, why?
Personally, I have never eaten meat in all my life.
One has to survive, I don't know why,
so one needs, kills the least thing that is a vegetable.
Right?
And I believe some scientists are gradually coming
to that point of view also.
Then you'll all accept it.
It seems to me the part of the past is the mental pattern of thinking.
And all these questions are Aristotelian thinking,
and you are using non-Aristotelian thinking,
and that seems to be why there is such a gap.
In other words, to look at something is to use a non-Aristotelian...
That's right, sir.
Well, then everyone here is talking Aristotelian thinking,
and you are using a non-Aristotelian thinking.
And that is the reason why there is such a gap.
That's right, sir.
Well, then everyone here is talking Aristotelian
and thinking Aristotelian,
and you are using non-Aristotelian tactics,
and therefore the gap is so complete, I'm amazed.
And I suggest that we all get non-Aristotelian
and then we can commune very closely.
That is the difficulty, sir. I know this.
Just a minute, sir, one moment.
Just a minute, sir, please look at it.
What that gentleman said was,
you are used to one particular formula,
particular series of languages with a certain meaning,
and the speaker has not that particular view.
So the difficulty lies in communication.
And we went into that.
He said the word is not the thing,
the description is not the described,
the explanation is not the explained,
and you keep on sticking to the explanation,
holding on to the word,
and that's why our difficulty is.
We see what violence is in the world.
It's part of fear, part of pleasure,
part of this tremendous drive for excitement.
And we want that,
and therefore we encourage society to give that to us.
And we blame the society,
whereas we are responsible for all this.
And we are saying, asking ourselves,
whether this violence which is such terrific energy,
can that energy be used differently?
Right?
To be violent needs energy.
Now, can that energy be transformed
or moved in another direction?
We are putting the same thing differently.
Now, look, any form of resistance is a waste of energy.
Right?
Because that breeds violence.
Resisting one nation against another nation,
one nation saying, I am better than you,
and so on, resisting.
The resistance between wife and husband,
resistance, you understand,
is energy which breeds division and therefore violence.
Now, understanding that, seeing the truth of that,
that energy now becomes entirely different, doesn't it?
No?
Mark, K.
Q. How can a person observe the balance between
the power of the mind and the existence of the person?
K. All right, that's a good question.
How can one observe the total process,
the totality of anything,
without the division, without resistance?
Right?
Have you ever observed totally anything?
Anything, it doesn't matter what.
An ant moving across the floor, have you watched it totally?
Or do you step on it, or throw it out?
Have you watched it very, very closely?
I am afraid you haven't.
Have you ever watched a tree totally?
Which means not saying how beautiful it is,
or how ugly it is, or I wish I had it in my garden.
Have you ever watched it totally?
Have you ever watched the cloud with the light on it,
marvellous sight, completely?
Or you say, this lovely cloud, let's go and have tea.
No, sir, do look at it.
Have you ever watched your wife totally, or husband?
No, sir.
And therefore if you watch totally there is no resistance.
It is this inattention that breeds resistance.
Oh, come on, sir.
Q. When you look at another person totally,
doesn't it seem to make them uncomfortable?
K. Ah, when you watch a person totally,
you make the other person rather uncomfortable.
I am afraid you do,
because they don't want you to look at him totally.
But you can do it casually.
So, please, sir, come back.
What we are discussing is really quite serious,
I wish you would pay attention to it.
You want to be entertained, I am afraid,
I am not the kind of person who wants to entertain.
Q. Sir, non-violence that is absolute is another thing.
Violence itself is an aberration of what it could be.
K. Yes, if you want to put it that way.
Sir, look, what we are saying is,
violence is a form of energy.
And love is also a form of energy.
Love without jealousy, without anxiety, without fear,
without bitterness, without all the agony that goes with love.
Now, violence is energy,
love hedged about, surrounded, contained with jealousy,
all that, is another form of energy.
Now, to transcend both, go beyond both,
is also another energy.
It is the same energy moving totally in a different direction
and dimension. Right?
Q. But wouldn't both of those energies be the same?
K. We are saying that, sir. No, we are saying, look, sir.
Non-Aristotelian language.
Q. No, I am saying, is love with jealousy, is actually violence?
K. Of course it is.
Q. So in other words, you have two energies and you have the violence.
K. It is the same energy, sir.
Madame, let's say more...
Q. At what stage and under what conditions is a certain individual
to go into psychic practices and experiences,
and to what extent? Please.
K. What are you saying, madame?
Q. When should we have psychic experience?
K. When should we have psychic experience?
What has that to do with violence?
Do, please, just listen.
When should you have psychic experience?
Never.
Do you know what it means to have psychic experiences?
To have the experience, extra-sensory, perceptive experience,
you must be extraordinarily mature,
you must be extraordinarily sensitive,
and therefore extraordinarily intelligent.
And if you are extraordinarily intelligent,
you don't want psychic experiences.
Sirs, do look.
Give your heart to this, please,
because human beings are destroying each other through violence.
The husband is destroying the wife,
and the wife is destroying the husband,
though they sleep together, walk together.
Each lives in isolation,
with his own problems, with his own anxieties,
and this isolation is violence.
Now, when you see all this so clearly in front of you,
see it, not just think about it.
When you see the danger of it, you act, don't you?
Look, when you see a dangerous animal, you act, don't you?
There is no hesitation,
there is no argument between you and the animal.
You just act, you run away or do something.
Here we are arguing.
You don't see the tremendous danger of violence.
You only see the end result of violence, which is the bomb.
So if you actually, with your heart,
see the nature of violence and see the danger of it,
you are finished with it.
But you see, now how can one point out the danger of it
if you don't want to see it?
Either Aristotelian, non-Aristotelian language won't help you.
Yes, sir?
Q. There have been groups in India, here and other places
where living in a society which is violent,
they said, we will not be violent.
K. Yes, sir.
Q. There are groups in India, here and other places
where living in a society which is violent,
they said, we will not be violent.
But we are going much further than that.
They may not have violence against the community,
but they are violent in themselves.
You don't see the point.
Q. Sir, I feel that I see what you are saying,
and I have tried that, of watching violence in myself
about naming.
The gentleman who asked the first question
about having been in a concentration camp,
being a vegetarian, how do we meet violence?
I feel like, how do we meet violence in other people?
Do we do it in the same way?
K. How do you meet violence in other people?
That is really quite a difficult problem, isn't it?
My neighbour is violent, violent towards me,
how shall I deal with him?
Turn the other cheek? He is delighted.
What shall I do?
If you ask that question – do please, I am asking this seriously –
would you ask that question if there was no violence in you?
No, do listen, sir, please do listen to this question.
If in your heart, in your mind there is no violence at all,
not a spot, no hate, no bitterness,
no sense of fulfilment, no wanting to be famous,
you know, no violence at all.
Would you ask that question how you would meet the neighbour
who is violent,
or you would know then what to do with your neighbour?
Others may call what you do violent,
but you may not be violent. You follow?
You have no violence.
And at the moment your neighbour acts violently,
you will know how to deal with it.
But the third person watching you might say,
by Jove, you are also violent.
But you know you are not violent.
So what is important is to be for yourself
completely without violence.
And it doesn't matter what another calls you.
You know it, you know it, you know it.
It doesn't matter what another calls you.
You know in your heart you are not.
Q. Isn't the belief in the unity of all things
just as human as the belief in the division of all things?
K. Belief in the unity of all human beings.
No, sir, don't believe.
Why do you want to believe in the unity of all human beings?
We are not united, that is a fact.
Why do you want to believe in something which is non-factual?
Sir, that brings up the whole question of belief.
You see, that is just it.
You have your belief and another has his belief.
And we are fighting, killing each other for belief.
The communist has his belief, Stalin had his belief,
and he destroyed millions.
Now, why do you have any belief at all?
You have belief because you are afraid.
No?
Do you believe that the sun rises?
It is there to see it, you don't have to believe.
So belief is a form of division,
therefore belief is violence.
So the mind, to be free of violence, implies all this,
freedom from everything that man has put into another man.
Belief, dogma, rituals, my country, your country,
your god and my god, my opinion, your opinion, my ideal,
all those help to divide human beings
and therefore breed violence.
And though religions have said, organised religions have said,
have said, preached unity of mankind,
each religion thinks it is far superior than the other,
the Baptists against the – you know, you know it all very well.
Q. Sir, who said unity of all things?
K. Who said unity of all things?
Sir, there is a unity of all things
only when you know what love is.
When there is love in your heart you will know it,
don't talk about unity.
When you are destroying your neighbour, don't talk about unity.
Q. But sir, you have spoken now of freedom,
you have spoken of freedom from.
Can you tell us about freedom to?
K. You have talked about freedom from.
Will you say something about freedom to?
Freedom from or freedom to is not freedom.
Freedom is freedom, not from something towards something.
Right?
Q. I interpreted what you were talking about in unity
that those who preach unity are actually aiding the division.
K. Quite right, sir.
Q. Is the actual understanding of this
the relative scene and the effect that you actually understand?
K. Yes, sir.
Sir, look, when you see danger you do, you act.
If you see the danger of violence, see it, you then act,
but you don't see the danger of violence
because you are used to it, like belief.
You say, yes, why shouldn't I believe?
My opinion is as good as yours,
my opinion is as good as your opinion.
So, any divisive, dividing element in human beings
is productive of violence.
If one realises, understands that,
and then one watches – belief, will, desire to fulfil, to become,
you follow? – all these are breed violence,
which doesn't mean at the end of it
you live a vegetable kind of life.
On the contrary, you live in a totally different dimension,
which we'll talk about tomorrow when we talk about meditation.
Q. Sir, you've established that elimination of violence
will make it possible for everyone to be able to cope
with the material existence much easier.
In other words, to be able to completely eliminate the ego self.
Well, that's all very fine and it's very good,
but are you saying that this is the purpose for human life,
this is our purpose for living,
is just to be able to cope with the material existence?
Partly, sir, but also when you say,
is this the purpose of living?
Why do you want a purpose for living?
Living is its own purpose.
Why do you want a purpose?
You see, again, look at it. Look, sir, what we have done.
Each one has his own purpose. Right?
The religious man, his purpose, the scientist, his purpose,
the family, its purpose, and so on, divide it.
So, the life of a man who has a purpose is breeding violence,
because they divide.
Sir, it's all so clear and simple when you see the fact.
Q. Sir, you've employed the tool of reason and logic up to this point,
and probably throughout your entire lifetime,
to answer the questions that have come up in your mind.
Have you never reached a point to where you have found
a definite limitation to reason and logic?
K. Sir, I hope I'm not logical.
Logic must go to a certain extent.
One must think logically, sanely, healthily, up to a point, reason.
But after that, beyond that, there is much more.
Q. And you're saying that there is such a thing as an intuitional life.
K. Ah, wait a minute.
Now, when you use the word intuition, that's a dangerous word.
Intuition may be your own desire, your own wish,
saying, and you can say, that's my intuition.
What we are talking about is living a life in this world,
not escaping from this world, a life of non-violence,
a life, a really truly religious life,
not an intuitive life,
a life in which there is no conflict,
and a mind that's completely silent.
Again, we'll go into that when we talk about meditation.
Q. You said that life should be complete order,
and that complete order is precise in mathematics.
Therefore, wouldn't life in complete order be logical,
because mathematics is logical?
K. Sir, sir, when I said mathematical, I said in the sense,
you know, the highest form of mathematics is surely order.
Only in that sense. Yes, madame?
Q. Last night you spoke of disorder,
and when one realises it is disorder,
and, you know, he can learn, if he looks at disorder,
and he can find order through that, and learn the discipline,
and in a way become enlightened, because you are just being aware,
you're not naming it like when somebody calls you an ass,
and you become aware.
But then, why sometimes do people,
even when they're endowed with this new freshness,
all of a sudden there's a lack of carrying it out,
carrying out the action, kind of falls back and becomes stagnant?
K. You are asking, are you, madame,
why isn't one enlightened all the time?
Q. Why?
K. Isn't that it?
Q. Well, it seems like it's a ladder.
K. Why doesn't enlightenment last a long time?
Why doesn't intelligence function all the time?
Why does one occasionally become stupid?
You know, you see, at the end of this talk
you will go away being violent.
What's the point of meeting together
if this remains in your heart and in your mind?
We spent an hour and a half trying to see what violence is,
and understanding it and really eliminating it, going beyond it.
Sir, it's half past twelve. Don't you think we'd better stop?
Yes, sir. Just one more question, that'll be enough.
Q. I would like to hear you express yourself.
You said there you receive energy from violence.
Isn't the selfless love of one brother to another
the deadliest weapon in the world
because of people's total inability to energise themselves in this?
And can you not take the hate
and energise that hate and return love?
K. I don't quite understand, sir.
Q. I don't quite understand it myself.
I'm trying to get my head in this place.
Love, I'm convinced, is the deadliest weapon in the world.
And when you're coping with a neighbour that's violent,
can you not take that violence
and use it as a source of energy to return love?
K. No, sir, I don't quite see this point.
Look, sir, I'm your neighbour, you hate me, or I hate you.
And you say to me, you're asking whether you cannot take my hate
and turn that energy into love
and respond to man who hates with love. Is that it?
Q. When you return love, if the only way you can...
Really, when I asked this question, I wanted your awareness on this.
To be able to take violence and hatred and use that as a...
K. Why should I use it, sir?
Q. To be able to cope with it.
K. We dealt with that question just now when the gentleman asked,
what shall I do if there is no violence in me
when my neighbour is violent?
To that we said,
if you really have no sense of violence,
then you will know what to do when your neighbour is violent.
Don't determine now what you will do.
Don't have a formula for a life which is not violent.
If you have a formula, then that very formula is breeding violence.
I think you better stop, sir.